A Guide to the Rockefeller Foundation records, officers' diaries, RG 12, A-E FA391
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller Foundation records, officers' diaries, RG 12, A-E
1911-1992
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller Foundation
FA391
51.3 Cubic Feet
Actual extent is unknown.
Biographical/Historical note
Rockefeller Foundation diaries:
Officers of the Rockefeller Foundation in New York and its staff members in the field often visited educational, scientific and research institutions and laboratories in many parts of the world to maintain contacts and assess work being done. Officers and field staff frequently conferred with government officials regarding the operation of the RF's programs. In order to preserve accurate records for the guidance of other RF officers, those who carried on these activities kept diaries of their day-to-day contacts and impressions. These diaries were sent to the RF office, where they circulated among officers and staff to the extent deemed advisable.
Rockefeller Foundation:
The Rockefeller Foundation was established by act of the New York State Legislature approved by the Governor on May 14, 1913, "to promote the well-being of mankind throughout the world." Between 1913 and 1928 the China Medical Board, the International Health Board, and the Division of Medical Education functioned as divisions of the Foundation, concentrating on the administration of programs in public health and medical education. A Division of Studies was created in 1923 to handle projects outside the medical field. These early years were experimental as the new foundation studied the methods of philanthropy and explored its relationships with other Rockefeller boards.
Although the Rockefeller Foundation is the largest and best known philanthropy founded by the Rockefeller family, it was neither the first nor the last to be established. The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research (1901), the General Education Board (1902), the Rockefeller Sanitary Commission for the Eradication of Hookworm Disease (1909), and the Bureau of Social Hygiene (1911) all existed earlier. When the Foundation was created, the Sanitary Commission was disbanded. After the establishment of the Foundation, the Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial (1918) and the International Education Board (1923) were created.
The Rockefeller boards and their programs were reconsidered and reorganized in 1927-1928 in order to avoid overlapping programs. The International Health Board of the Foundation was disbanded and an International Health Division was organized. The China Medical Board, Inc., was established as a separately incorporated institution, and the China Medical Board of the Foundation ceased to exist. The Division of Studies was dropped and the Division of Medical Education was phased out. The Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial was combined with the Foundation and the Spelman Fund of New York was chartered to continue activities of the LSRM that were not absorbed by the Foundation. The International Education Board was disbanded.
As a result of this reorganization, the Foundation adopted a program which included public health work (administered by the IHD), the advancement of knowledge in the medical and natural sciences (in part taken over from the IEB), the social sciences (formerly the field of the LSRM), and the humanities and arts (shared with the GEB). The Rockefeller Institute and the Bureau of Social Hygiene were not affected by the reorganization. The program adopted by the Foundation at this time remained basically the same for the next twenty years.
As its files accumulated, the Foundation maintained a card index recording the names of institutional and individual grantees and correspondents. A microfilm copy of this index is available at the Archive Center.
File Plan note
RG 12
Organization of the Foundation's archives:
RG 1 Projects
RG 2 General Correspondence
RG 3 Administration, Program and Policy
RG 4 China Medical Board
RG 5 International Health Board/Division
RG 6 Field Offices
RG 7 Treasurer's Office
RG 8 Comptroller
RG 9 Personnel
RG 10 Fellowships
RG 11 Information Services
RG 12 Diaries
RG 13 Oral Histories
RG 14 Counsel
RG 15 Secretary
RG 16 Minutes and Officers Actions
RG 17 Dockets
RG 18 Declinations (100F)
RG 19 Non-textual Materials
RG 20 Communications Office
Scope and Contents note
Rockefeller Foundation officers' diaries:
Diaries are of two types: regular daily diaries, and special trip diaries. Some diaries have indexes, which are bound in the annual volume; indexing was not a requirement but was left to the discretion of the officers, and not all diaries are indexed.
Diaries frequently contain information given in confidence, and were thus treated as confidential., The period covered is approximately 1911-1992.
Conditions Governing Access note
Officers' diaries are open for scholarly research provided that (1) the diarist is deceased and (2) the volume to be examined is at least twenty years old. All reasonable efforts will be made to determine the fate of the diarist(s), but if such efforts are fruitless then the material will remain closed to scholarly research until the 100th anniversary of the officer's birth.
Other Finding Aids note
Other available finding aids describing Rockefeller Foundation records, Officers' Diaries include:
FA392 Rockefeller Foundation records, Officers' Diaries F-L.
FA393 Rockefeller Foundation records, Officers' Diaries M-R.
FA394 Rockefeller Foundation records, Officers' Diaries S-Z.
Arrangement
Alphabetically by surname.
Charities; Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations; Medical sciences; Public health; Race and society; Arts; African Americans; Life sciences; Humanities; Epidemics; Diseases; Philanthropy; Philanthropy -- United States
- Aitken, Thomas H. G.
  - 1946-1947 (Box 1)
  - 1948-1951 (Box 1)
  - 1954-1955 (Box 1)
- Albaugh, Leland G.
  - 1948 (Box 1)
- Allen (Shikoh), Jane
  - 1971-1973 (Box 2)
  - 1974 (Box 2)
  - 1975 (Box 2)
  - 1976-1977 (Box 3)
- Allen, LeRoy R.
  Biographical/Historical note
  Born 1913.
  Conditions Governing Access note
  Restricted - RF Officer Diaries.
  - 1957- 1961 November (Box 3)
  - 1961 December-1962 (Box 4)
  - 1963-1965 (Box 4)
  - 1968 (Box 4)
- Anderson, Charles R.
  India; Colombia; Trinidad
  - 1952-1955 (Box 5)
    Colombia; India; Trinidad
- Anderson, Richmond K.
  - 1947-1950 (Box 5)
  - 1951-1952 (Box 5)
  - 1953-1954 (Box 6)
  - 1955 (Box 6)
  - 1956 January-June (Box 6)
  - 1956 July-December (Box 7)
  - 1957 January-June (Box 7)
  - 1957 July-December (Box 7)
  - 1958 January-April (Box 8)
  - 1958 May-December (Box 8)
  - 1959 January-May (Box 8)
  - 1959 June-December (Box 9)
  - 1960 January-June (Box 9)
  - 1960 July-December (Box 9)
  - 1961 January-March (Box 10)
  - 1961 April-August (Box 10)
  - 1961 September-December (Box 10)
  - 1962 January-March (Box 11)
  - 1962 April-December (Box 11)
  - 1963 January-May (Box 11)
  - 1963 June-December (Box 11)
  - 1964 (Box 12)
- App, Alva A.
  - 1983-1987 (Box 12)
- Appleget, Thomas B.
  Thomas Baird Appleget was born in Hightstown, New Jersey, in 1893. In 1913 Appleget enrolled at Brown University and distinguished himself as associate editor of The Brown Daily Herald and editor of the Brunonian. He was a member of Phi Beta Kappa and graduated summa cum laude.
  Upon graduation in 1917 Appleget took a position as Executive Secretary to Brown University President William Faunce. In 1918 he left this position to serve as an infantryman in the U.S. Army, but following the end of World War I he returned to Brown, where he was eventually promoted to Assistant to the President and worked in the areas of public relations and student recruitment.
  In 1926 Appleget became Executive Secretary to John D. Rockefeller, Jr. (JDR Jr.), who was also a Brown graduate. This position included diverse responsibilities related to the management of Rockefeller philanthropies. Appleget was also called upon for an array of special assignments, including a memorable 1926 flight with Charles Lindbergh. During a spring blizzard, Appleget was asked to accompany Lindbergh on a mission to deliver a newly developed Rockefeller Institute serum to aviator Floyd Bennett, who lay dying of pneumonia in a Quebec City hospital. Although Appleget and Lindbergh arrived safely, Bennett eventually died of his illness.
  In 1929 Appleget left the service of JDR Jr. when he was appointed vice president of the Rockefeller Foundation (RF). Working out of the New York City office, Appleget led a number of initiatives with the Foundation, including the Refugee Scholars Program from 1940 to 1945.
  In 1940 Appleget married Sara Elizabeth Love of North Carolina, and together they settled in Greenwich, Connecticut.
  In 1949 Appleget returned again to Brown University, this time as Vice President, in which capacity he focused on public relations and fundraising.
  Appleget retired from Brown University in 1959. He died of emphysema in 1982 at the age of 89.
  China
  - 1929 (Box 12)
  - 1930 (Box 13)
  - 1931 (Box 13)
  - 1932 (Box 14)
  - 1933 (Box 14)
  - 1934 (Box 14)
  - 1935 (Box 14)
  - 1936 (Box 15)
  - 1937 (Box 15)
  - 1938 (Box 15)
  - 1939 (Box 15)
  - 1940 (Box 16)
  - 1941 (Box 16)
  - 1942 (Box 16)
  - 1943 (Box 16)
  - 1944 (Box 16)
  - 1945-1946 (Box 17)
  - 1947-1948 (Box 17)
  - 1949-1950 (Box 17)
- Arbab, Farzam
  - 1974-1977 (Box 18)
- Arnold, Virginia
  Colombia; Nigeria
  - 1959 (Box 18)
  - 1960 (Box 18)
    Nigeria; Colombia
  - 1961 (Box 19)
  - 1962 (Box 19)
  - 1963 (Box 20)
  - 1964 (Box 20)
  - 1965 (Box 21)
  - 1966-1967 (Box 21)
- Baird, Guy B.
  - 1958-1961 (Box 21)
  - 1962 (Box 22)
  - 1963-1966 (Box 22)
  - 1967-1969 (Box 22)
  - 1969 December- 1970 February (Box 23)
  - 1970 March-May (Box 23)
  - 1970 July (Box 23)
  - 1970 September-November (Box 23)
  - 1971 March-July (Box 23)
  - 1971 September-December (Box 23)
- Bakeman, George W.
  - 1926-1927 (Box 23)
- Balfour, Marshall C.
  India; Philippines; Greece; China; Southern States
  - 1939, 1943-1944 (Box 23)
  - 1945-1949 (Box 23)
  - 1951-1954 (Box 24)
  - 1955-1956 (Box 24)
  - 1957-1958 (Box 24)
  - 1958-1960 (Box 24)
- Barnard, Chester I.
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
  The archival material has been reformatted. Access to the original archival material is restricted. Digital files and user copies of the microfilm are available for scholarly access.
  Chester I. Barnard brought years of experience as a successful and respected business executive to the Rockefeller Foundation (RF) when he was named president in 1948. His organizational skills proved effective during his short four-year tenure as he presided at a time of transition, when the Foundation sought out new directions in programming in the postwar era.
  Chester Barnard was born in Malden, Massachusetts, in 1886. He lost his mother when he was five years old, but his father, a mechanic, encouraged philosophical debate and emphasized the importance of education. After completing grammar school, he apprenticed as a piano tuner, a trade that helped to fund his education.
  Barnard used his earnings from piano tuning to fund his way through Mount Hermon Preparatory School and eventually earned a scholarship to attend Harvard University. At Harvard he continued working while pursuing a degree in economics. While he excelled at Harvard, nearly completing a four-year course in three years, he left school before graduating. Barnard was unable to fulfill an obligatory science requirement while working to pay his living expenses.
  He left Harvard in 1909 and immediately went to work at the American Telephone and Telegraph Company (AT&T) as a statistician. From this entry-level position he rose rapidly through the ranks to become vice-president of the Bell Telephone Company of Pennsylvania in 1926 and president of New Jersey Bell Telephone Company in 1927. Yet Barnard was not just a successful executive he also applied himself to the study of management. He authored two seminal books in the field of management theory. The Functions of the Executive (1938) and Organization and Management (1948) focused on topics of company organization and human relations. The Functions of the Executive is considered to be a classic in the field and has been translated into several languages.
  During World War II, Barnard contributed to the war effort by lending his considerable administrative and management talents to organizing and presiding over the United Services Organizations, Inc. (USO), a job which later earned him the Presidential Medal for Merit. In the postwar period, Barnard became interested in atomic energy, serving as a consultant to the United Nations Atomic Energy Commission and co-authoring a report on the international control of atomic energy.
  In 1948 Barnard left Bell to accept the position of president of the RF. This appointment capped nearly a decade of involvement with the Foundation, where he had served as both a Foundation Trustee and a member of its Executive Committee.
  Barnard remained at the RF for four years, retiring in 1952. Following his retirement from the RF, he continued working for the improvement of society. In 1957 he was appointed a member of the New York City Board of Health. As a member of this Board, he helped to create the city's new health code.
  In addition to his interests in management, energy, health and social responsibility, Barnard possessed a life-long passion for music. This passion led him to help found and support the Bach Society of New Jersey and the Newark Arts Theatre.
  Chester Barnard died in 1961 at 74 years old.
  - Index, 1948-1952; Rockefeller Foundation; Barnard, Chester Irving; 3 pages (Reel M Bar 1, Frame 1, Box 25)
    Scope and Contents note
    Index to diary 1948-1952. Organized by the person, organization, or institution interviewed
    indexes (reference sources)
  - 1948 August 18-1952 May 29, Barnard, Chester Irving; Rockefeller Foundation; 81 pages (Reel M Bar 1, Frame 4, Box 25)
    Organized by interview, entries for this period record the meetings and telephone conversations that took place between Barnard and seekers of RF funding or fellowships. Noteworthy interlocutors (and their positions at the time) include James B. Conant, the president of Harvard University; Lewis W. Douglas, United States Ambassador to the United Kingdom; Joseph C. Grew, former U.S. Ambassador to Japan; and John J. McCloy, U.S. High Commissioner for Germany. Lengthy conversations with John J. McCloy include McCloy's perceptions of postwar Germany and attitudes toward German reorientation. Barnard's own opinion of postwar Germany is included in the section entitled "Notes on German Attitude," and is located within notes on his trip to Europe. A personal conversation between John D Rockefeller Jr. and Barnard is embedded within the entries. The discussion centered upon JDR's opposition to the phrase "distributing wealth for the public good" as was written in a draft of the RF history.
    Diaries
- Barnes, Allan C.
  - 1970-1975 (Box 26)
  - 1976-1977 (Box 26)
- Barnish, Guy
  - 1969-1978 (Box 27)
- Bates, Marston
  Albania; Egypt; Colombia
  - 1948-1949 (Box 27)
- Bauer, Johannes H.
  - 1935-1939 (Box 27)
  - 1940-1944 (Box 28)
  - 1945-1947 (Box 28)
  - 1948-1951 (Box 28)
  - 1952 (Box 29)
  - 1953-1954 (Box 29)
- Beach, Byron
  - 1921 (Box 29)
- Beard, Mary
  Mary Beard devoted her entire life to improving the field of nursing. Her persistent efforts played a key role in the greater professionalization of the field, both in the United States and worldwide.
  Born in 1876, Beard enrolled in the New York Hospital School of Nursing in 1899. She graduated in 1903 and immediately took a position as a home nurse with the Visiting Nurse Association (VNA). By the time Beard left the VNA in 1910, she had been serving as the director of the organization. She worked briefly at the Laboratory of Surgical Pathology at Columbia University before heading to Boston in 1912. There she became director of the Boston Instructive District Nursing Association. This position allowed her to organize the medical care of Boston's poor and to focus her attentions on prenatal and maternity care. In the same year Beard also helped to found the National Organization for Public Health Nursing, an organization devoted to the improvement of nursing practices and education. She served as president of the organization from 1916 to 1919 while simultaneously chairing a Council of National Defense Medical Board's Committee on Public Health Nursing during World War I.
  In 1924 Beard began working with the Rockefeller Foundation (RF). She quickly proved instrumental in the Foundation's efforts to improve the standards of nursing education worldwide. In 1931 she was named Associate Director of the RF's International Health Division (IHD). In this role, Beard investigated nursing education in both Europe and Asia and develpoed new programs to improve training in these regions. One of these programs involved creating opportunities for women from Europe and Asia to study nursing in North America, where they would receive the knowledge and skills necessary to train others in their home countries.
  In 1938 Beard assumed the directorship of the American Red Cross Nursing Service and chairmanship of the Office of Defense Health and Welfare Service's Subcommittee on Nursing, where she organized the education and assignment of nurses for wartime duty. She retired from the Red Cross in 1944 and died in New York City in 1946.
  Middle East; Asia; Europe
  - 1925 December 4-1926 December 31, Rockefeller Foundation; Beard, Mary (Box 30, Reel M Bea 1, Frame 1)
    Organized according to interview or visit, entries for this year record the meetings and conversations that took place between Beard and professionals and students in the field of nursing. Nursing education programsboth domestic and internationalare discussed and schools of nursing located within the U.S. are visited and surveyed. The subject matter of the diaries includes nursing and public health; women's health; child health; maternal care; child care; and nursing education. A copy of "Listening On" a pamphlet published by the National Organization for Public Health Nursing (October 1926) is also included in this diary. (New York, Yale School of Nursing New Haven)
    Diaries; Nursing care plans; Nursing; Yale University. School of Nursing
  - 1927, Rockefeller Foundation; Yale University. School of Nursing; Beard, Mary; 197 pages (Box 30, Reel M Bea 1, Frame 171)
    Organized according to interview or visit, entries for this year record the meetings and conversations that took place between Beard and professionals and students in the field of nursing. A theme during this year's entries is the advancement of the nursing profession in the US and abroad. International nursing fellows are hosted at US and Canadian institutions and the state of public health in communities with and without nursing personnel is assessed. Other subject matter includes general public health; hospital organization; nursing organization within wards; nursing higher education; and nursing professionalization. (Yale School of Nursing New Haven, Toronto)
    Diaries; Public health nursing; Public health
  - 1928, Beard, Mary; Yale University. School of Nursing; Rockefeller Foundation; 130 pages (Box 30, Reel M Bea 1, Frame 386)
    Organized according to interview or visit, entries for this year record the meetings and conversations that took place between Beard and professionals and students in the field of nursing. Beard tours nursing establishments across the country including hospitals, nursing universities, and clinics and reports on the state of nursing at each institution. Specific subjects addressed include nursing theory; nursing and public health education; the professionalization of nursing; the cost of nursing to hospitals; the organization of the nursing service; and the activities of committees dedicated to nursing affairs.
    Public health nursing; Nursing; Nursing care plans; Diaries
  - 1929, Beard, Mary; Rockefeller Foundation; 141 pages (Reel M Bea 1, Frame 537, Box 30)
    Organized according to interview or visit, entries for this year record the meetings and conversations that took place between Beard and professionals and students in the field of nursing. Developmentand proliferationof public health nursing is the principal objective of Beard's visits, interviews, and activities for this year. Concerning domestic development, Beard surveys the nursing profession in a number of U.S. cities, and concerning international development, Beard is involved in sponsoring international women to study in the US on RF fellowships. The integration of African-Americans into the nursing profession is also discussed throughout the entries.
    Nursing; Nursing care plans; Diaries; Public health nursing
  - 1930, Beard, Mary; Rockefeller Foundation; 148 pages (Box 30, Reel M Bea 1, Frame 696)
    While on an extensive tour of Europe and Asia, Beard meets with international nursing professionals and surveys the state of nursing education in a wide array of countries includingbut not limited toChina, India, Singapore, Israel, Egypt, and the United Kingdom. Upon her return, Beard continues her work managing the education of RF fellows from foreign countries; promoting the development of public health nursing in the U.S and abroad; and standardizing the education of nursing professionals. A map entitled "China, Siam, Indo-China, and Chosen," is embedded within the entries and is dated 1915.
    Public health nursing; Diaries; Nursing; Nursing care plans
  - 1931, Beard, Mary; Rockefeller Foundation; 108 pages (Reel M Bea 1, Frame 864, Box 30)
    Organized according to interview or visit, entries for this year record the meetings and conversations that took place between Beard and professionals and students in the field of nursing. Beard is heavily involved in advising RF nursing fellowsboth American and foreignand discusses their educational development and experiences throughout the entries.
    Diaries; Public health nursing; Nursing; Nursing care plans
  - 1932, Rockefeller Foundation; Beard, Mary; 88 pages (Box 30, Reel M Bea 1, Frame 972)
    Temporarily based at the RF Paris Office, Beard meets with fellow public health nursing officer Elizabeth Crowell and tours various European cities where the RF has invested funds in nursing and/or public health programs. Entries record her impressions of programs and fellowship recipients as well as suggestions for the future. Cities included in the European tour include Warsaw, Krakow, Vienna, Graz, Cluj, Budapest, Debrecen, Skoplje, Belgrade, Zagreb, and Rome. Upon returning to the NY office, Beard continues her duties as a public health nursing consultant for various RF programs across the United States. Included in this years' entries are preliminary surveys and impressions of public health in various cities located in Pakistan, India, and Sri Lanka.
    Public health nursing; Nursing care plans; Nursing; Diaries
  - 1933, Rockefeller Foundation; Beard, Mary; 90 pages (Box 30A, Reel M Bea 2, Folder 1)
    Organized according to visit and interview, entries for this year record the meetings and conversations that took place between Beard and professionals and students in the field of nursing. Entries record her various impressions of maternity hospitals, child welfare centers and nursing/medical schools in Burma, India and Sri Lanka. Upon her return, discusses trip abroad, fellowships for public health nurses and nursing education. Also, Beard is heavily involved in advising RF nursing fellows-both American and foreign- and discusses their educational development and experiences throughout the entries.
    Nursing care plans; Nursing; Diaries; Public health nursing